原創翻譯  雙語字幕
最新連載海外影視劇下載
請登陸 www.YYeTs.com
僅供交流學習  禁止商用盈利
翻譯     天天   根總迷弟
翻譯     Eunice
時間軸     Ethan-澤生
校對     Ethan-澤生
后期     8T
總監     somehacker  Ethan-澤生
根據薩羅·布萊爾利的書籍
《漫漫回家路》改編
根據真實故事改編
薩羅
Saroo.
快  快跑
Come on, come on!
上來
Get up!
快點  抓緊了  薩羅  抓住
Come on, quickly! Hold it properly, Saroo, catch!
下去
Get down!
古度  守衛追來了
Guddu! The guards!
嘿  小子  快下來
Hey, boy, get down!
下來  小子
Go! Get down, boy!
印度  坎德瓦
-薩羅  -古度
- Saroo. - Guddu.
薩羅
Saroo.
我來了
I'm here!
我們今天能得到很多錢
We will get a lot of money today
我們偷到了很多煤
We've got a lot of coal!
給我看看
Show me!
這么多啊
Ohhh, so much!
你總是說我很小  但你看我多聰明
You kept telling me how little I am but see how clever I am?
沒錯  你的確很聰明
That's right, you are!
你從那么高的地方跳下去了  真了不起
You jumped from so high! What a leap!
是啊  真的很高
Yes, great heights!
給他們些牛奶  兩袋
Give them some milk, two packets
古度  我想吃糖耳朵
Guddu, I want some jalebis!
總有一天  我會給你買很多糖耳朵
One day I will buy you some jalebis
我們把整家店都買下來
We'll buy the whole shop!
哈哈  好的
Ha, alright
-現在應該走哪邊  -左邊
- Which way should I go now? - Left, left!
-現在呢  -右邊
- Which way now?  - Right, right
你想喝牛奶嗎
Do you want to drink some milk?
我搞到牛奶了哦
I got some milk!
簡直是魔法
It's magic
告訴我  你們是怎么搞到牛奶的
Tell me now how did you get the milk?
說實話哦
Be honest
古度  薩羅
Guddu? My Saroo?
我不喝
No
好了  夏綺拉  我得工作了
Okay, Shekila, I have to work now
誰來照顧夏綺拉
Who's going to look after Shekila?
我的薩羅
My Saroo?
來  吃吧
Come, eat
睡吧  睡吧
Sleep... sleep
你要離開多久
How long will you be away for?
你今天做得很棒
You did a really good job today
我也想去
I want to come too
-要多少天  -我要去一周
- How many days? - I'm going for a week
-誰來照顧夏綺拉  -卡魯會的
- Who's going to look after Shekila?  - Kallu will be here
-你太小了  扛不動包  -我可以扛得動任何東西
- You're too small to lift bales  - I can lift anything
古度
Guddu!
我能一起去嗎
Can I come too?
你太小了  做不了這種事
You're too small, you can't do this
我能扛得動任何東西
I can lift anything
薩羅  我跟你說過了
Saroo, I've told you
那是夜班工作  小孩子干不了
it's night work, not for kids
走吧  你太小了
Go, go, you're too small
薩羅  放下吧
Saroo, leave it
我還能扛得動這個
I can lift this
好吧  行
Okay, fine
嘿  古度
Hey, Guddu!
嘿  你還好嗎  山卡
Hey! How are you, Shankar?
-薩羅  快  醒醒  -我想睡覺
- Saroo, come on, wake up now!  - I want to sleep
-薩羅  醒醒  -我想睡覺
- Saroo, wake up!  - I want to sleep
-薩羅  -我想睡覺
- Saroo  - I want to sleep
-薩羅  醒醒  -別煩我  我在睡覺呢
- Saroo, wake up  - Don't annoy me, I am sleeping
都是我的錯  是我把你帶來的
It's my fault, I brought you here
你太小了  做不了夜班工作
You're too young for the night work
真的很晚才開工  你永遠沒法工作
It's so late you will never be able to work
薩羅  薩羅
Saroo, Saroo...
我去看看工作的事  好嗎
I'm going to find out about work, okay?
我等下就回來
And then I'll come back
你在這里等著  別到處亂跑
You wait here, don't go anywhere
古度
Guddu?
給我買回一百個糖耳朵哦
Just bring back a hundred jalebis
你想吃糖耳朵
You want jalebis?
-給我買回兩百個糖耳朵  -糖耳朵
- Bring me two thousand jalebis! - Jalebis?
你就在這等著  別亂跑
Just wait there, don't go anywhere
古度
Guddu?
救救我
Help me!
古度  古度
Guddu! Guddu!
快來人救救我
Someone save me!
救救我
Help me!
Help!
古度
Guddu!
媽  我很愛你
Mum, I love you very much
古度  我很想你
Guddu, I miss you very much
2號站臺的列車是一輛退役列車
The train on platform two is a decommissioned train
不再載客
It is not taking passengers
救救我
Save me!
快來人救救我
Someone help me!
放我出去
Get me out of here!
救救我
Save me...
放我出去  救救我
Get me out of here! Save me!
救救我  救救我
Save me! Save me!
西孟加拉邦  加爾各答
位于坎德瓦以東1600公里處
開門
Open!
古度
Guddu!
媽媽
Mum!
古度
Guddu!
媽媽
Mum!
甘尼斯塔萊
Ganestalay?
我想回家  我家在甘尼斯塔萊
I want to go home, Ganestalay
甘尼斯塔萊
Ganestalay?
甘尼斯塔萊  我想回家
Ganestalay? I want to go home
我聽不懂  說孟加拉語  我聽不懂你在說什么
I don't understand! Speak Bengali! I don't understand you
讓開  搞什么  你聽不懂孟加拉語嗎
Move! What's the matter? You don't understand Bengali?
甘尼斯塔萊
Ganestalay?
別在那上面走  你會掉下來的
Don't walk on that, you're going to fall off
-你聽得懂印地語嗎  -是的
- Do you understand Hindi? - Yes
-你要去哪兒  -我得回家  我迷路了
- Where are you going? - I have to go home, I am lost
-你是從這邊來的嗎  -我也不知道
- Did you come from this way or that? - I don't know which way
那你怎么回家
Then how will you go?
-你叫什么名字  -薩羅
- What's your name? - Saroo
我叫諾奧
My name is Noor
你餓了嗎
You're hungry?
來吧
Come on
進來吧  快點
Come inside, come on!
來吧
Come on!
我不得不做這些
I have to do all this
給男人們做午餐盒飯
make lunch boxes for all the men.
人總得填飽肚子
You have to feed your stomach, you know.
每個人都得工作
Everybody has to work
我會幫我媽搬石頭
I help my mum to carry rocks
你媽媽是搬石頭的
Your mum carries rocks?
瞧這是什么
What is this?
喝吧
Just drink
給我留點哦
Leave some for me!
抹點肥皂
And now a bit of soap
有個叫羅摩的人  他是個大好人
There is a man and he is called Rama he's a very good man
他幫助所有人  肯定也會幫助你的
He helps everyone, he will help you too
他明天早上會過來
He's coming tomorrow morning
他會幫我找到我媽嗎
Is he going to help me look for my mum?
他會幫助你找到你媽
He's going to help you look for your mum
閉上眼睡覺吧
Close your eyes go to sleep
睡吧
Sleep
我的寶貝
Oh, my baby
你在睡覺嗎
Were you sleeping?
我很好奇你是從多遠的地方漂泊來的
I wonder what worlds you've travelled.
-你是羅摩嗎  -是的  但不是那個神
- Are you Rama? - Yes, but not the God
來躺下吧
Come and lie down
靠近點
Come closer
你知道嗎  我是從很遠的地方來見你的
Do you know? I've come to meet you from really far away
我想帶你去一個好地方
and I want to take you to a really nice place
你會帶我去找我媽嗎
Are you going to take me to Mum?
從哪里  我們會試著去找你媽
And from there we're going to try and look for your mum
我今晚回來  然后我們就去找
I'll be back tonight and then we'll search.
起來
Get up!
靠近點
Come closer
說"謝謝"
Say "thank you"
謝謝
Thank you.
你做得很好
You've done well
他完全是我們想找的類型
He's exactly what they're looking for.
怎么了  你沒喝嗎
What happened? You didn't drink?
你不喜歡嗎
You don't like it?
你怎么不高興
Why are you down?
喝下吧
Drink this
靠近點
Come closer.
薩羅
Saroo!
好孩子
Good boy!
去搬小點的
Go pick up the small ones
好孩子
Good boy!
好孩子  真是好孩子
Good boy! Good boy!
好孩子
Good boy!
誰是我的好孩子  是誰啊
Who's my good boy? Who is it?
對不起  媽媽
I'm sorry, Mum
兩個月后
我從餐廳出來  開始跟他說話
So I came out of the cafe and started talking to him
我意識到他根本不會說孟加拉語
I realized he doesn't speak a word of Bengali
他只會說印地語
He only speaks Hindi
我就問他來自什么地方
I asked him where he was from?
他只會回答一個詞  叫甘尼斯塔萊
He replied with only one word "Ganestalay"
我從沒聽說過
I've never heard of it
甘尼斯塔萊
Ganestalay
聽著  甘尼斯塔萊位于哪個區
Okay, which district is Ganestalay in?
甘尼斯塔萊位于哪個區
Which district is Ganestalay in?
-你母親叫什么 -媽媽
- What is your mother's name?  - Mum
-你叫什么名字  -阿米塔
- What's your name? - Amita
這是個很可怕的地方
This is a very bad place
有人可以離開這里嗎
Does anybody ever leave here?
我見到過
I've seen it
-你離開以后要干什么  -我要買個手表
- What are you going to do once you leave? - I'm going to buy a watch
你們寫了嗎
Did you write it?
喂  尚迪普  你在干什么
Hey, Shonedeep! What are you doing?
停下
Stop!
-停下  立刻停下  -尚迪普
- Stop! Stop right now! - Shonedeep!
你為什么這么淘氣
Why are you being so naughty?
尚迪普
Shonedeep!
給我過來  我要好好打你一頓
Come with me, I'm going to give you a good beating!
你休想逃脫懲罰
You won't get away with this!
尚迪普  起來  快點
Shonedeep! Come on, come on!
尚迪普  起來
Shonedeep! Come on!
看這邊  看這邊
Look this way, look this way
是我  沒事  我帶他走
It's me, it's okay, I'll take him
明天天亮前把他送回來
Bring him back before morning
星星都出來  尋找月亮
All the stars came out in search of the moon
命運悲慘的人都來到大街上
The ill-fated came out on the streets
星星都出來  尋找月亮
All the stars came out in search of the moon
它們出來尋找賊
They came out in search of the thief
星星都出來了
The stars came out
薩羅  我是蘇德太太  來坐下
Yes, Saroo, my name is Mrs. Sood, come sit here
我的任務就是確保
It's my job to make sure that
只要孩子們能有別的去處  就不要在這里遭罪
there isn't a single kid here who should be somewhere else
所以我才會來這里
That's why I'm here
這里的人都不喜歡我
People don't like me here
看看這個
Look at this
我們已經打聽你的來歷很長時間了
We have been asking around about you for a long time.
我們在報紙上刊登了啟事
We have published it in the newspaper
在加爾各答所有的報紙上都刊登了
In all the newspapers in Calcutta
有1500萬人看了這報紙  那可是很多人
15 million people read this paper, that's a lot of people.
但卻沒有收到任何回復
But we haven't had a single reply
我家在很遠的地方
My home is really far
一個回復都沒有
Not one reply
-我媽媽也沒回復嗎  -沒有
- What about Mum? - No
你媽媽也沒有
Not even Mum
古度呢
Guddu?
薩羅
Saroo...
澳大利亞有一戶人家
We have found a family over in Austral
愿意照顧你
who want to look after you
你知道澳大利亞在哪兒嗎
Do you know where Australia is?
你想看看他們嗎
Would you like to see them?
來  我指給你看
Come, I'll show you
來坐著
Come sit here
你看這個  這是約翰
Look, look at this, this is John
這是蘇
and this is Sue
這個...
This...
這是他們的家
This is their home
他們住在塔斯馬尼亞島
They live in Tasmania
那是個小島  那里的人都很好
A small island and everyone there is really nice
他們看上去都很好  不是嗎
They are such nice people! Aren't they?
這個你拿著  好好保管  好嗎
Keep this with you and keep it safe, ok?
薩羅
Saroo...
孩子  你不能待在這里
Son, you can't stay here
你真的幫我找我媽媽了嗎
Did you really look for my mum?
到處找過了
Looked everywhere
你將會擁有一個美好的家
You'll have a nice home
澳大利亞是個好地方
Australia is a great place
每個人都有一張布巾嗎
Does everybody have a napkin?
-這叫餐巾  -餐巾
- This is called a "serviette" - Serviette
像這樣鋪在腿上
Lay it down on your lap like this
食物就不會掉在你的衣服上
so that food doesn't fall on your clothes.
也不會毀了你的衣服
So it doesn't ruin them
我會教你們怎么用西式餐具吃飯
I'm going to teach you how to eat using cutlery
我會問你們
I will ask you,
每樣東西用英語怎么說
and you will tell me in English what each thing is called
這個怎么說
What do you call this?
叉子
Fork.
叉子  沒錯  很好
Fork. Yes good.
-那這個叫什么  -"好子"
- What do you call this? - Nice
是刀子
Knife.
很好
Good.
那這個呢
And this?
勺子  勺子
Spoon. Spoon.
好了  曼尼莎  你來告訴我  這叫什么
Okay, Manisha, you tell me, what is this?
好好想想
Try to remember
鹽  鹽
Salt. Salt.
非常好
Very good.
福椒粉
Payper!
-是胡椒粉  -胡椒粉
- Pepper. - Pepper.
胡椒粉
Pepper.
好的  好的
Okay, okay.
澳大利亞  霍巴特
謝謝
Thank you.
薩羅
Saroo.
這就是你的爸爸媽媽了
This is your mum and dad
去打個招呼
Say hello
你好  我是索米婭
Hello, I'm Swarmina.
你好  我是約翰  這位是蘇
Oh hello. I'm John, this is Sue.
你好啊
Hello there.
你好  這是送給你的
Hello. Here this is for you.
一路飛來還好吧  還好嗎
Good on the plane? Eh, good?
蘇
Sue...
-她是  -媽媽和...
- This is... - Mummy and...
爸爸
Dad.
我們很高興能見到你
And we're so happy to meet you.
一艘船
A boat.
太棒了
Amazing.
放松  放松
Gently... gently...
這就是你住的地方
This is where you live.
在那邊  那是客廳
Down there, that's the living room.
那是電視
Television.
你知道電視是什么嗎
Do you know what a television is?
可以播放畫面
Pictures.
水
Water.
你可以打開它
You can open it.
你覺得我應該幫他撕開嗎
Do you want me to cut it up for him?
福椒粉
Payper!
什么
What was it?
福椒粉
Payper!
沒錯  胡椒粉  說得對  這個呢...
Yes, pepper. That's right and...
-醬料  -醬料
- Sauce! - Sauce?
-是鹽  -鹽
- Salt. - Salt.
非常好啊
Very good.
嗨
Hi.
你經歷了很多事才來到這里  對吧
So, you've come a long way, haven't you? Hmm?
小家伙
Little one.
我相信那一定很不容易
I'm sure it hasn't been easy.
有一天你會告訴我一切的
One day you will tell me all about it.
你會告訴我所有  你是誰  關于你的一切
You'll tell me everything. Who you are, everything.
我永遠都會聆聽的
I'll always listen.
永遠
Always.
一年后
保持不動  沒錯
Stay, yeah yeah...
沒錯  就是這樣
Yeah, that's... that's it.
-手下留情  好嗎  -沒錯
- Go easy on me, yeah? - Yeah.
來吧伙計
Okay mate.
-媽媽  爸爸  -集中注意
- Mum... Daddy... - Pay attention.
他要投了  來吧伙計
Here he comes! Come on mate!
她出局了
She's out!
我的天啊
Oh my gosh!
你們怎么能這么對我
How did you do this to me?
好了
All right.
爸爸  媽媽  薩羅
Dad, mum, Saroo...
曼塔希
Mantosh.
是的
Yes.
又見面了
Hello again!
薩羅  我的天啊  快看看你
Aw, Saroo, my goodness, look at you!
你好
Hi.
我的天啊  我們非常激動
Oh my gosh, we've been so excited!
這是曼塔希
This is Mantosh.
你好
Hi.
你好  曼塔希
Hey Mantosh...
這是薩羅  我叫蘇
This is Saroo. I'm Sue...
這是薩羅  你的哥哥
This is Saroo, your brother.
-他是約翰  -你好啊  伙計
- And John... - Hello mate!
快給曼塔希看看你的禮物
Show, show Mantosh what you've done.
他畫了幅畫
He did a picture, Yeah...
-坐了很久的飛機吧  -是的  是的
- It's been a long flight? - Yes, Yes, Yes.
你一定餓了
You must be hungry.
我們要去吃點東西
We're going to get something to eat.
你想和我們一起嗎
Would you... like to join us?
好的  那真是太好了
Oh alright, ok that would be nice.
快停下  快停下
Stop, stop, stop, stop...
不要這樣  沒事的  我知道  沒事的
No no no, It's alright. I know it's Okay.
停下  快停下
Stop it! Stop it! Stop it! Stop!
-快來  -我知道  我知道
- Come on... - I know I know...
-不  不要  -小家伙
- No no no. - Hey mate.
沒事  去玩玩具吧
It's okay. Just play with your toys.
不  不  不要打了  伙計
No, no, no, don't hit mate.
不要打自己了  別打腦袋  別打腦袋
Don't hit yourself. No no no.. Not your head.. Not your head.
-好了  -你沒事了  沒事了
- Come on - You're alright, you're alright...
沒事了
It's okay.
沒事的  伙計
Come on, it's okay, man.
看  那有艘船  現在好多了
Look, there's a boat. It's better now.
我沒事
I'm okay.
我沒事的
I'm all right .
20年后
-我們會想你的  -好啦
- We're gonna miss you. - Yeah.
只是去墨爾本而已
It's only Melbourne.
是誰要漂洋過海了
Who is across the water?
薩羅
Saroo...
我們漂亮的孩子
Our beautiful boy!
希望這能滿足你的一切期望
May this bring you all that you could wish for.
是啊  并且還不止呢
Yeah, and then some.
謝謝媽媽  謝謝爸爸
Thanks mum. Thanks dad.
從你進入我們生命中的那一刻
From the moment you came into our lives...
-媽媽  -不  不  讓我說完
- Mum... - No no no, let me finish.
從你進入我們生命中的那一刻
From the moment you came into our lives...
你滿足了我們所有的期望
You were all that we could have hoped for.
甚至超出了我們的期望  真的
More, more than we hoped for, really.
同時也下了更多的功夫  毫無疑問
And, er, more work, that's for sure.
你抓住了每一個機會
You really embraced every opportunity.
我們為你感到驕傲  兒子
We're very proud of you, son.
為你人生中的下個篇章感到十分的驕傲和激動
Very proud and very excited with this next chapter in your life.
干杯
Cheers!
-祝你成功  -抱歉打擾了
- To success! - Excuse me guys?
你們還在等人嗎  不然我把這個盤子撤了
Are you still waiting on someone? Or can I take this plate away?
-是的  可以撤下去了  -不  放這吧
- Yeah, you can take it away. - No no no, you can leave it.
不  拿走吧
No, take it.
我想放在這  謝謝
I'd like to keep it. Thank you.
你不會真的認為他會出現吧
You don't really think he will turn up, do you?
好了  別說了  兒子
No, just leave it, son.
這酒很好喝
That's a nice one.
確實不錯  這酒是本地的特產
Yeah it's a good one. This one's a local one.
曼塔希
Mantosh?
抱歉  我沒有去吃午餐
Sorry, I didn't meet lunch.
你是去讀什么課程來著
What's that course again?
酒店管理
Hotel Management.
所以到時候你會去干什么
So you're going when to do what?
管理酒店嗎
Manage a hotel!
祝你愉快
Have fun!
你有什么賬單需要付嗎
Any bills you need to pay?
你學成回來后可以給我們一份工作
You can give us a job when you come back.
我不在家的時候  能不能別亂來
Please could you not do anything while I'm away?
那會讓媽媽更加傷心的
That's going to make mum more unhappy than you already do.
伙計
Mate...
你覺得我為什么會離開家
Why do you think I stay away?
墨爾本
我們視自己為酒店管理學校中的聯合國
We see ourselves as United Nations of hospitality schools.
我們傾向于認為
And we'd like to think
我們倡導的是一種全球化  均衡化的觀念
we teach a global and balanced perspective.
你們來到這里  是因為你們懷有夢想
You're here because you have a dream.
我們的存在  就是為了幫助你們實現夢想
We're here to help make that dream a reality.
是的  我明確地看到酒店行業
Yeah and I saw firsthand how the hospitality industry
可以為有需要的社區提供基礎設施
can really bring infrastructure to communities that need it.
但我也看到了它們造成的許多問題
But I also saw a lot of problems that they cause,
也正因此  社區團體
which is why community groups need to be,
需要全程參與
involved every step of the way,
他們也應該受到重視
and they need to be taken seriously.
然后
And?
我想幫助
I guess I want to help
推動這件事  幫他們發聲
facilitate that and help give them a voice.
薩羅
Saroo.
我想經營酒店  好把利潤都賺進自己口袋里
I want to run hotels, so I put all the profits into my pocket.
先說說你來自哪里吧  好嗎
Well, let's start with where you are from? Shall we?
你出生在澳大利亞嗎
So, born in Australia?
是  不是...
Yeah No, er...
加爾各答
Calcutta.
我有家人在加爾各答  我的表親們特別糟糕
I've got family in Calcutta. My cousins are quite bad.
哪個地區
Which part?
我是被領養的  我不算是印度人
I'm adopted. I'm not really Indian.
但是你喜歡板球  對吧
But you like cricket though, right?
你喜歡板球啊
Ah, you like cricket...
你支持澳洲隊還是印度隊
You go for the Aussies or the Indians?
只支持澳洲隊
Only the Aussies, mate!
這就有意思了
This is going to be interesting.
好了  薩羅
Okay, Saroo...
你為什么選這門課
Why did you choose this course?
你還希望從中獲得什么
What else do you want to get out of it?
-你好  -你好
- Hi. - Hey!
抱歉
Sorry.
-歡迎  -請進  請進
- Welcome. - Come in. Come in.
你好
Hi!
嗨  你好嗎
Hi, how are you?
你們喜歡吃印度菜嗎
Do you guys like Indian food?
只準備了印度菜  只有這些
That's all we have. That's all we have.
-聞起來好香啊  -我試著學別人...
- It smells so great. - I tried to copy someone...
你有沒有跳過寶萊塢舞蹈
You've ever done Bollywood dance?
-只動一條腿這樣  -對  一條腿
- Oh, just like, one leg. - Yeah, one leg...
比如我說"手電筒"  用你們的語言怎么說
Okay, well, like, I say flashlight. What do you say?
-口袋燈  -口袋燈[法語]
- Lampo de poche. - Lampo de poche?
-口袋燈  -手電筒的說法...
- Lampo de poche. - Flashlight is er...
你們怎么叫
What do you say?
電筒
Torch.
如果你想用手抓著吃
If you want to eat with your hands,
就要用馕盛著  像勺子一樣
you need to use the naan, like a spoon.
-用叉子吧  -不  讓他用馕
- Use a fork. - No, let him use the naan.
你們怎么說的士
So how do you say taxi?
-的士  -的士
- Taxi. - Taxi.
這個詞在所有語言里都一樣
It is the same in every language.
你想用叉子嗎  薩羅
Do you want a fork, Saroo?
好啊
Yeah!
他像我父親一樣
He's like my father.
-你要不要再來一瓶啤酒  -要  謝謝
- You want another beer? - Yes please, thank you.
古度  我想吃糖耳朵
Guddu, I want some jalebi.
你好啊
Hello...
你沒事吧
You okay?
薩羅
Saroo?
我并不是來自加爾各答
I'm not from Calcutta.
我迷路了
I'm lost.
豪拉火車站很大  你當時一定嚇壞了
Howrah station is enormous, you must have been freaking out.
有一次我去布里朝圣  經過那里
I once went through there on a pilgrimage to Puri,
結果我兩次沒趕上火車
and I missed my connection twice.
你那時候不會說孟加拉語嗎
And you didn't speak Bengali?
我當時連那種語言叫什么都不知道
I didn't even know it was called that.
-你在火車上待了多長時間  -好幾天吧
- How long were you on the train? - A couple of days.
好幾天嗎
A couple of days?
薩羅  你的家鄉在哪里來著
Saroo, what was your hometown again?
甘尼斯塔萊
Ganestlay.
我一定是記錯了  因為沒有這個地方
I must have had it wrong because it doesn't exist.
但你一定還記得別的線索吧
But there must be something else that you do remember.
那個站臺
The platform...
我睡著的地方  有一個很大的雨水收集箱
I fell asleep on, there's a big rain tank.
那里離甘尼斯塔萊只有幾站路
It was only a few stops from Ganestlay.
成千上萬的火車站都有雨水收集箱
There are thousands of stations with rain tanks.
好吧  這是很久以前的事了
Okay, it was a long time ago.
你有沒有聽說過一個新項目  叫谷歌地球
Have you heard of this new program, Google Earth?
它很神奇  可以幫你找到世界上任何一個地方
It's incredible, you can find any place from anywhere.
聽我說  我們可以查出
Listen to me, we can find
當時客運列車的時速是多少
out how fast passenger trains went back then.
我們用那個時速
We take that speed,
乘以你坐火車的小時數
multiply by the hours that you were on the train.
就成了
That's it!
我們能得出搜索半徑
We create a search radius.
然后在這范圍內  找出那個有雨水收集箱的車站
And inside there, you will find the station with the rain tank.
沒錯  可是搜索印度
Yeah, but it will take a
所有的火車站  要花上一輩子的時間
lifetime to search all the stations in India.
我有說所有的火車站嗎
Did I say all the stations?
好吧  哪怕只找一半
Ok, even half the stations.
各位  我真的不想談論這件事
Really guys, I don't want to talk about this.
你的父母有找過你嗎
Did your parents try to find you?
-怎么了  -他們當然找過他
- What? - They tried to find him.
不  我的意思是
No I just mean like,
如果他們找過你  可能會留下書面線索
if they tried to find him, maybe they left like a paper trail.
什么書面線索
What paper trail?
-他連自己姓什么都不知道  -我媽不識字
- He didn't know his surname. - My mum couldn't read or write.
她做什么工作的
What does she do?
勞工  她抬石塊的
A labourer, she carried rocks.
你媽媽嗎
Your mum?
我媽大約四年前去世了
My mom died about four years ago now.
我很遺憾
I'm sorry.
我爸爸還是很生她的氣
My dad is still so angry at her.
當然不是因為她病了
Not for getting sick, obviously...
而是因為她不肯做化療
but just for refusing chemo.
但她很了解自己  清楚自己想要的生活方式
But she just knew herself, you know? She knew what her terms were
以及如何度過余下的時間  所以...
and she knew how she wanted to live, so...
大概就是無法接受吧
Just couldn't accept that, I guess.
那你又是什么感覺
And how do you feel?
我很想她
I just miss her.
你覺得巴拉特關于搜索半徑那個提議怎么樣
And what do you think of Bharat's search radius idea?
那是什么意思
What was that?
這是你的舞步嗎  你是這樣跳舞的嗎
Is that your dance? Is that how you dance?
天啊
Oh, God!
客運列車速度
塔斯馬尼亞島  霍巴特
你不能再這樣下去了
You can't keep going on like this.
讓我來幫你
Let me help you.
我們去跑步吧
Let's go for a run.
什么
What?
露西
Lucy!
過來
Come here.
等一下
Hold on.
抽筋了
Got a cramp.
你騙我  你作弊
You lied! You cheat.
我從來沒給別人看過這個
I never show anybody this.
為什么  很美啊
Why? They're beautiful.
我真的很喜歡畫畫  這是我的小愛好
I do enjoy it. My little hobby.
看看曼塔希啊
Oh wow, look at Mantosh!
他今晚會來  我真的很高興
I'm so glad he's coming tonight.
狂妄無禮的小東西
Cheeky little thing.
精力十足
Pure energy.
但是很了不起
But incredible.
真有愛
So sweet!
他一向難以控制  可是
He's been hard to control, but...
卻非常聰明
very, very smart... and very...
只要他能學會控制自己  他做什么都能成功
I mean, he could do anything if he just learned to control that energy.
他任何事情都能做到
He could do it, and do it all.
薩羅對他的保護欲很強
Saroo is very protective of him.
我很幸運
I've been blessed.
非常幸運
Very blessed.
你媽媽給我看了你以前那些獎杯
Your mom showed me all your old little trophies.
媽媽  你不是吧
Mum, you didn't.
我都不知道你以前那么喜歡運動
I didn't know you were so athletic.
那些只是一半而已  還有很多在車庫里
That's only half of them. There's plenty more in the garage.
你去哪兒  伙計
Hey, where you going, mate?
把煙抽完
Finishing my smoke.
現在我想讓他離開沙發
I can barely get him off...
-都很難  -露西
- ...the couch these days. - Lucy!
你為什么就不能告訴他們
Why can't you just tell them...
-你最近在干什么  -不要說
- what you've been up to? - Don't!
告訴我們
Tell us.
他們會理解和支持你
They will understand and they will support you.
什么事  快說吧
What? Come on.
嘿  吃晚餐了
Hey, um, dinner!
趕快趁熱吃吧
Better eat it, while it's hot.
-你餓了嗎  -是的
- You hungry? - Yeah.
怎么了
What?
我錯過了什么
What have I missed?
沒什么
Nothing.
-她看起來不高興  -她沒有不高興
- She looks upset. - She's not upset!
你又不知道我的感受
You don't know how I feel.
薩羅無所不知
Saroo knows everything.
他可是專家
He's an expert.
他是個經理
He's a manager.
你為什么來這里
Why are you here?
因為他是你的兄弟
He's here because he's your brother.
不  他不是
No, he's not.
-我們不一樣  -住口  薩羅
- We're different. - Hey, now now, Saroo!
薩羅
Saroo...
好了
All right.
沒事的
It's all right.
別這樣
Hey hey, no no...
沒事了  沒事了  停下
It's all right, It's all right... Stop!
不要動
Don't move.
沒事了
It's okay.
干得好啊
Nice one, mate.
沒事了  沒事了  深呼吸  深呼吸
It's okay mate, It's okay, just breathe, mate. Just breathe...
我恨他對你造成的傷害
I hate what he's done to you.
對不起
I'm sorry.
薩羅
Saroo!
Saroo.
薩羅
Saroo!
吻我
Kiss me.
別這樣  求你了
Stop, please.
看著我
Look at me.
Look at me!
-晚點再談  行嗎  -你魂不守舍的
- Can this wait? - Where are you?
能不能等我們回家再談
Can this wait 'til we get home?
-行嗎  -家
- Yah? - Home?
什么家
What home?
你是指我獨自待在一個房間
You mean, where I'm alone
你獨自待在另一個房間的那個地方嗎
in one room and you're alone in another room?
來啊
Come on.
別這樣  露西
Stop, Luce. Stop it.
來啊
Come on.
求你了
Please.
薩羅
Saroo!
你必須面對現實
You need to face reality!
你說的現實是什么意思
What do you mean? Reality?
你能想象我的心情嗎  知道自己親哥哥
You have any idea what it's like knowing my real brother...
和母親每一天都在找我
and mother spend everyday of their lives looking for me?
我的親哥哥每天怎樣呼喊著我的名字
How every day my real brother screams my name!
你能想象
Can you imagine the pain
他們不知道我的下落的痛苦嗎
they must be in for not knowing where I am?
25年  露西  25年了
25 years, Luce. 25!
你為什么不告訴我這些心結
Why didn't you tell me that's was happening for you?
我們在優越的生活中  放縱享受著
And we swung about in our privileged lives.
那讓我覺得惡心
It makes me sick.
我必須找到家
I have to find home.
他們必須知道  好嗎
They need to know, okay?
我從未阻攔過你
I've never stopped you.
我想幫忙
I want to help.
我不能再這樣下去了
I can't do this anymore.
你值得更好的
You deserve more.
別這樣
Don't you do that!
你不能這樣  這都是你錯  可不怪我
Don't you dare do that! This is on you, not on me.
薩羅  你在嗎  伙計
Saroo, you there, mate?
明天是單日國際板球賽
It's One Day International tomorrow.
你想來的話就來吧
You can come over if you like?
我是想告訴你  我修好了船柄
I meant to tell you, I fixed the tiller.
我們為什么不帶它出去  我們可以開去海岸
Why don't we take her out? We can head up the coast?
嘿  薩羅
Hey, Saroo...
伙計  你媽媽她不...
Mate, your mum's not, um,
聽著  我們找不到曼塔希  他又失蹤了
look, we've lost track of Mantosh, he's missing again.
你知道她有多擔心
You know how worried she gets.
我們知道你辭了工作  伙計
We know you quit your job, mate.
我們很擔心你  兒子
Just worried about you, son.
我最近時不時就去看看它
I've been visiting her.
每天晚上我順著那些街道走回家
Every night I walk those streets home.
從壩上走回家
Home from the dam.
從車站走回家
Home from the station.
我現在知道了...
I know now...
路上走的每一步
...every single step of the way.
我想象著...
And I imagine that I'm...
我在它耳旁輕語
...whispering in her ear...
我在這  沒事了
I'm here, it's alright.
她是什么樣的
What was she like?
很美
Beautiful.
紐約怎么樣
How was New York?
都一樣
It's the same.
所以  你為什么回來了
So, what brings you back?
我拿到經費了
My funding came through.
太棒了
It's great!
看吧
See...
他們知道你有多棒
They know how good you are.
我很想你
I miss you.
我見到你媽媽了
I saw your mom.
她不是很好
She's not doing very well.
我擔心  如果我告訴她我在找家她會崩潰的
I'm worried, it would kill her if she knew I was searching.
你低估她了
You underestimate her.
她需要你
She needs you.
不  給我5盧比  我把這些都搬走
No, give me five rupees then I'll carry them all
好吧  你贏了  拿著吧
Okay, you win, take this
他當時搬著西瓜  沒看到車過來
He was carrying a watermelon and didn't see it coming
怎么了
What?
如果你找到了家  他們卻都不在了怎么辦
What if you do find home and they're not even there?
你還會不停地去搜尋嗎
And you never stop and keep searching?
你不知道過了這么久發生了什么
And you don't know what happens over time,
世事變遷  整個世界都在變
things change, and entire worlds change.
我別無選擇
I don't have a choice.
留下來
Stay.
我不能
I can't.
站在那別過來
Stay right there
你不是應該照顧好他的嗎
Weren't you supposed to look after him?
你去哪了
Where were you?
你不愛他了嗎
Don't you love him?
約翰和曼塔希乘船出去了
John heard Mantosh is out on the boats.
去抓龍蝦了
Doing a lobster run.
他明天回來
He's due back tomorrow.
所以他會賺很多的現金  又要整天喝酒了
So he'll be flushed with cash, back on the hard stuff.
我很抱歉你不能有自己的孩子
I'm sorry you couldn't have your own kids.
你說什么
What are you saying?
我們
We...
并不是白紙一張
weren't blank pages, were we?
像你親生的孩子那樣
Like your own would have been.
你領養的不只是我們  也領回了我們的過去
You weren't just adopting us but our past as well.
-我感覺我們在害死你  -我可以生孩子的
- I feel like, we're killing you. - I could have had kids.
什么
What?
我們選擇不生孩子
We chose not to have kids.
我們想要你們兩個
We wanted the two of you.
那才是我們想要的
That's what we wanted.
我們想要你們兩個出現在我們的生活里
We wanted the two of you in our lives.
那是我們的選擇
That's what we chose.
那也是我愛上你爸爸的原因之一
That's one of the reasons, I fell in love with your dad.
因為我們都覺得
Because we both felt, as if...
這世界上的人已經夠多了
... the world has enough people in it.
生個孩子  并不保證任何事會變得更美好
Have a child, couldn't guarantee it will make anything better.
但是接受一個像你們這樣處于困境的孩子
But to take a child that's suffering like you boys were.
給你們一個機會
Give you a chance in the world.
那意義非凡
That's something.
我猜你們從來沒想過會有這么困難
I bet you never imagined it being this hard.
這并不是困難的問題
It's not a matter of hard.
這不是...
It's not a mat...
我只有這一條路可以走
There's only one path for me.
我是這么想的
And, that's how I think.
之所以會這樣是因為...
That's how this happened because...
在我歲12的時候
When I was 12,
我看到過一個幻象
I had a vision.
有些人會說那是精神崩潰  但是...
Some people would say, it was a breakdown. But it...
我父親是個酒鬼  你知道的  就好像
My dad was an alcoholic. You know that, and he was like
他不是一個好人
he wasn't a good man.
他那時失去了理智
He was out of control when I was...
而我當時站在屋后
I was standing at the back of the house.
我眺望著田野
I was looking out across this field.
希望這世界將我吞沒
And I just wanted the earth to swallow me up.
我...
And I...
我感受到一股電流  像是被電了一下
I felt an electric current, it was like a shock,
好像我渾身上下都在震顫
like a jolt through my whole body.
后來我看見...
And then I saw...
一個棕色皮膚的孩子
a brown skinned child
穿過田野
across that field.
他站在我的身邊
And he was standing beside me.
就在那里  我很強烈地感覺到了
And it was right there and I could feel it so strongly.
我人生中第一次感受到了美好的東西
And for the first time in my life I felt something good...
我感覺很愉快
I felt good.
我知道那是在指引我
And I knew it was guiding me.
我知道我會沒事的
And I knew that I was going to be fine.
那一刻我仿佛看到了我的未來  就在眼前
It was, as if, that moment I could see my future, right there!
因為我一直以為我可以把這個家聚在一起
Because I always thought that I could keep this family together.
現在...
And now...
現在我也不知道了
Now I don't know.
哪里...
Where...
-媽媽  -這是怎么回事  我不明白
- Mum... - What's happening? I don't understand.
你再也不跟我談心了
You don't talk to me any more.
我需要你  薩羅
I need you, Saroo.
曼塔希
Mantosh!
我為我晚餐時說得話道歉
Sorry for what I said at dinner.
甘尼希塔萊
Ganesh Talai...
Ganesh Talai.
甘尼斯塔萊
Ganestlay!
媽媽
Mum
我找到家了
I found home!
什么
What?
請你一定要等我
Please wait for me.
我在這
I'm here.
原來你一直就是在做這件事
So this is where you've been.
我不想讓你覺得我忘恩負義
I don't want you to feel, I was ungrateful.
我無時無刻不想告訴你
There wasn't a day, I didn't want to tell you.
薩羅
Saroo.
我真的希望她還在那等你
I really hope she's there.
她需要看看你長得多么漂亮
She needs to see how beautiful you are!
印度  坎德瓦
你好  我以前住在這里
Hi, I used to live here.
我..過去...
I...used to...
有什么要幫忙的嗎
Can I help?
這是我  我是薩羅
That's me. I'm Saroo.
我以前住在這里
I used to live here.
-你住這嗎  -是的  我以前住在這
- You lived here? - Yes I used to live here.
我在找古度  卡魯  夏綺拉
I'm looking for Guddu, Kallu, Shekila.
我的媽媽
My mother.
跟我來
Come.
去哪
Come where?
跟我來
Come with me.
來就是了
Just come.
薩羅
Saroo?
媽媽
Mum.
薩羅
Saroo?
Saroo...
薩羅
Saroo!
我找你找得好辛苦
Oh, how I looked for you!
薩羅
Saroo!
對不起
I'm sorry.
真的對不起
I'm so sorry.
是的  西瓜
Yes, the watermelon.
西瓜
Tarabuja!
西瓜  沒錯  西瓜
Tarabuja! Yes, tarabuja!
西瓜
Watermelon...
古度呢
And Guddu?
古度在哪
Where is Guddu?
他在哪
Where is he?
古度不在了
Guddu is no more.
他進入天堂了
He is with God.
這是夏綺拉
Shekila.
夏綺拉
Shekila?
-夏綺拉  -他是你哥哥
- Shekila? - He's your brother!
她長這么大了
She's so big!
是我  薩羅
It's me, Saroo.
真美
Beautiful.
你好  媽媽
Hi, mum.
我知道你已經睡著了
I know you will be sound asleep.
我只是想報個平安
I just want to say that I'm safe.
我平安無事  疑惑也都解開了
I'm safe and the questions have been answered.
不再是死胡同了
There are no more dead-ends.
我找到了我的親生母親
I found my mother, and...
她很感謝你們二位撫養我長大
she thanks you both for raising me.
她明白你們是我的家人
She understands that you are my family.
她知道我還活著  就很開心了
She's... happy, just knowing I'm alive.
我找到了她  但這不會改變你的身份
I found her, but that doesn't change who you are.
我愛你  媽媽
I love you mum...
十分愛你
so much.
還有你  爸爸
And you, Dad.
還有曼塔希
And Mantosh.
快來
C'mon!
我們走
Let's go!
快來
Come on!
薩羅
Saroo!
我們走
Let's go!
走快點
Walk faster!
我要走了  我要走了  我要走了
I'm going, I'm going, I'm going!
你會掉下去的
Oh, you're gonna fall!
薩羅·布萊爾利于2012年二月12日回到了甘尼希塔萊
他失蹤在外超過25年
25年前  就在他踏上那節空車廂的當晚
他的哥哥古度也去世了  在站臺附近被一列火車撞死
薩羅的母親卡姆拉  從未放棄過相信薩羅會回來
所以她從未搬過家
卡姆拉說當她兒子回來時  她震驚得"如遭雷擊"
她心中的幸福感"深似海洋"
薩羅得知  多年前  作為5歲的小孩
他一直把自己的名字拼錯了
他的真名叫"瑟盧"  意思是...
雄獅
-薩羅  -古度
- Saroo. - Guddu.
甘尼希塔萊
每年印度有超過8萬名兒童失蹤
我們正在跟一些杰出的組織合作  幫助印度和全世界的兒童
請登錄影片官網查看本片是如何幫助了流浪兒
歡迎加入我們  一起讓世界更美好